A Guide to the Governor Robert Brooke Executive Papers, 1794-1796
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor Robert Brooke Executive Papers, 1794-1796
Library of Virginia
40723
2.23 cubic feet
Governor's Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 5211-5214.
Miscellaneous Reel 5211 - 1794 Dec. 1-1795 May 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5212 - 1795 June 2-Dec. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5213 - 1795 County Officers-1796 June 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5214 - 1796 July 1-Nov. 25
Biographical Information
Robert Brooke was born in Spotsylvania County to Richard Brooke and Ann Hay Taliaferro Brooke around 1760. Educated in Edinburgh, Scotland, during the Revolutionary War, Brooke returned to Virginia in 1780 where he enlisted in a volunteer cavalry troop and was captured by the British at Westham in January 1781. Brooke returned to Spotsylvania County to practice law, later moving his office to Fredericksburg. In 1786, Brooke married Mary Ritchie Hopper (d. 1796) and settled on an estate in Fredericksburg which became known as Federal Hill. Brooke represented Spotsylvania County in the House of Delegates from 1791 until 1794. Upon the vacancy of the office of governor by Henry Lee to suppress the Whiskey Rebellion, the General Assembly elected Brooke governor on 20 November 1794. He was reelected for a second one-year term on 26 November 1795. Brooke County, now in West Virginia, was named after Robert Brooke when it was formed from part of Ohio County in 1796. Following his second term as governor, Brooke was elected to replace James Innes as attorney general of Virginia on 16 November 1796. He served as attorney general until his death on 27 February 1800.
Scope and Content Information
Robert Brooke's Executive papers are organized chronologically with undated items arranged at the end of each year. These papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during Brooke's two one-year terms as governor between 1 December 1794 until 1 December 1796. These records include correspondence written to James Wood who acted as Lieutenant Governor while Brooke was temporarily absent from office. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments for state positions; the Point of Fork Arsenal; defense of the frontier; resignations; arms & ammunition; Indian attacks; British & French ships in Virginia ports; the boundary line between Kentucky & Virginia; extraditions; the Houdon statue of Washington; state expenses & revenue; quarantine of vessels; foreign affairs; Revolutionary claims; elections; Presidential electors; the Capitol Building; the militia; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from Congress and the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; muster & pay rolls; accounts; oaths; pardons; receipts; election returns & certificates; qualifications; lists; depositions; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; treaties; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; applications; lists; opinions; and other sundry items. Note that files related to county officers for 1795 have been arranged alphabetically by county and separated to the end of the papers for that year.
Noteworthy correspondence originates from the United States government, Virginia State government, and miscellaneous sources. Prominent correspondents from the United States government include Henry Knox, Timothy Pickering, & James McHenry, Secretaries of War; Edmund Randolph & Timothy Pickering, Secretaries of State; Alexander Campbell, U.S. District Attorney General, Samuel A. Otis & John Beckley, Clerks of the Senate & House of Representatives, and President George Washington.
Governor Brooke received correspondence on numerous occasions from the United States War Department. On 5 December 1794, Henry Knox transmitted a resolution by John Beckley, Clerk of the U.S. House of Representatives, thanking the Virginia Militia for their service during the Whiskey Rebellion. Timothy Pickering replaced Knox as Secretary of War in 1795. Pickering writes on 6 January 1795 regarding the French ship Les Jumeaux which was armed and equipped at Philadelphia in violation of the U.S. neutrality law. Pickering also writes respecting bounty lands on the northwest side of the Ohio River for officers & soldiers of the Virginia Line on Continental Establishment (1795 June 13). In addition, Pickering responds to a letter from the Governor concerning establishing a small garrison of militia at Norfolk. According to Pickering, the President has no authority to call out the militia for the preservation of peace (1795 July 3). Lastly, Pickering writes regarding the pay of Charles Cist for printing regulations for the order and discipline of U.S. troops (1795 Sept. 14). James McHenry replaced Pickering as Secretary of War in 1796. In a letter dated 4 March 1796, McHenry acknowledges the receipt of the Governor's letter, along with the account & vouchers for militia & scouts on the Western frontier. William Simmons, in the Dept. of War Accountant's Office, corresponds with the Governor concerning the compensation by the United States to Virginia for the pay & subsistence of the militia, ammunition, and contingent expenses in the protection of the frontiers (1795 Sept. 17). On 14 March 1796, Simmons encloses a statement of differences on examination of the Virginia claims for pay, etc., in 1795. A letter from President George Washington dated 1796 Sept. 15 asks that his shares in the James River Company be applied to Liberty Hall Academy in rockbridge County (letter removed to the Vault - George Washington Papers).
Edmund Randolph, former Governor of Virginia, corresponds as Secretary of State. On 3 January 1795, Randolph transmits a proclamation of thanksgiving from the President (proclamation not included). In another letter of the same date, Randolph remarks on a letter from the Governor regarding the embargo. On 16 February 1795, Randolph writes about the capture of a pilot boat belonging to the British Consul at Norfolk. Randolph encloses copies of letters from Gen. Thomas Mathews to Governor Lee, Alexander Hamilton, Sec. of the Treasury, and orders from Mathews to Lt. Vaughan. On 8 May 1795, Randolph encloses letters and papers from George Hammond, British Minister Plenipotentiary, concerning French prizes taken by Rear Admiral Murray and an order for foreign ships to depart American ports. Included is a copy of a letter from Thomas Jefferson to Hammond regarding French & British ships in American ports and the treaty with France to admit prizes & repair French ships in U.S. ports. The next day, Randolph encloses additional copies of letters from Hammond, along with a declaration & affidavit by Thomas Butler regarding the French prizes taken by Admiral Murray. Finally, Randolph discusses the practice of British ships of war impressing American seamen (1795 May 20). All copies of letters were transcribed by George Taylor, Jr., Chief Clerk of the Department of State. Timothy Pickering served as Secretary of State upon the resignation of Randolph on 19 August 1795. On 20 January 1796, Pickering writes to Pierre A. Adet, French Minister Plenipotentiary, with respect to U.S. neutrality. Pickering also encloses a translation of a letter he received from Adet regarding the purchase of flour & horses by the English in Virginia.
Alexander Campbell, District U.S. Attorney, provides his opinion on the following subjects: the unlawful detention of a mariner by a British vessel of war (1795 Jan. 25), the delivery of a fugitive of justice from Pennsylvania and deserters from a British ship of war at Norfolk (1795 Jan. 25), and the Unicorn, a suspected privateer outfitting at Gloucester (1795 June 26). In addition, Samuel A. Otis & John Beckley periodically transmit journals of the proceedings of the U.S. Senate & House of Representatives (1795 April 13 & 25, & 1796 July 28).
Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include Archibald Blair, Clerk of the Council; Samuel Coleman, Assistant Clerk of the Council of State; James Innes, Attorney General; Charles Hay, Clerk of the House of Delegates; Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate; William Hay, Robert Goode, & William Foushee, etc., Directors of Public Buildings; Robert Quarles, Superintendent of the Point of Fork Arsenal; Thomas Newton & Willis Wilson, County Lieutenants; John Pendleton, Jr., Auditor of Public Accounts; and Jacquelin Ambler, Treasurer.
Archibald Blair & Samuel Coleman, as Clerk & Assistant Clerk of the Council, communicate with the Governor frequently through the Council Office. Blair offers the advice of the Council regarding the account against the U.S. for the Western defense, reimbursement for the Springfield expedition, the printing of German military regulations, and orders for scouts in Ohio & Harrison Counties (1795 Jan. 14). Blair also writes G. Deneale denying his request to keep arms given to the light infantry under his command at Winchester to use against the insurgents (1795 Feb. 11). On 14 July 1795, Blair submits the order of the Council for ordering out the militia from Norfolk & Portsmouth to prevent disorder or insurrections from the frequent migrations of negroes. Lastly, Blair provides the advice of the Council concerning witnesses against Archer Branch in North Carolina (1796 Feb. 15). Coleman mainly writes concerning military finances including the account of Hugh Caperton for ammunition (1794 Dec. 2) and Capt. William Lowther's pay abstract & muster roll (1795 March 5). On 12 May 1795, Coleman writes the Governor requesting that the office of Keeper of the Capitol not be taken from his father, Wyatt Coleman. His father writes a similar letter on the same date. On 4 December 1795, Coleman requests additional compensation for completing a list of officers & privates of the Continental Line. Shortly thereafter, Coleman was appointed Adjutant General and asks the Lieutenant Governor for an apartment in the Capitol to perform his new duties (1795 Dec. 14).
During James Innes' absence in 1794 & 1795, John Marshall provides his opinion on the militia law as Attorney General of Virginia (1794 Undated). Upon Innes' return, Marshall writes as counsel to Lord Fairfax concerning the case of the Commonwealth against him in the Court of Appeals (1795 March 2). On 23 April 1795, Innes writes that he will be unable to attend this trial in the Court of Appeals due to illness. Innes provides an opinion on such topics as the improper trial of William John Thweatt who was found guilty of horse stealing (1795 April 7), proceedings against Mr. Johnson for the alleged murder of Mr. Jeffers (1796 Jan. 13), and the power of the Governor to procure the attendance of necessary witnesses from the Territory South of the Ohio River (1796 Feb. 3). On 21 June 1796, he remarks on the assignment of the Solicitor's Office for the use of the Attorney General. Again, on 17 July 1796, Innes writes that he must be absent from office because of health problems. He adds that he has asked Mr. Warden to discharge the duties of his office. Innes was forced to resign in a letter to the Governor dated 13 November 1796.
Charles Hay, Clerk of the House of Delegates, and Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate, often submit legislation and qualifications of election to the Governor. Noteworthy legislation includes a resolution to inquire about the "lucrative office" accepted by James Innes in the General Government (1794 Dec. 16). Included in these papers are the qualifications for the election of Spencer Roane as Judge of the Court of Appeals in place of Henry Tazewell (1794 Dec. 2), the election of Jaquelin Ambler as Treasurer (1794 Dec. 17), Paul Carrington as Judge of the General Court in place of Spencer Roane (1794 Dec. 17), Robert Brooke as Governor (1795 Nov. 26), Robert Brooke as Attorney General (1796 Nov. 16), and Samuel Shepard as Auditor of Public Accounts in place of John Pendleton (1796 Nov. 16). A letter from John Wise, Speaker of the House of Delegates, encloses sundry resolutions for proposing certain amendments to the U.S. Constitution (1795 Dec. 19).
William Hay, Robert Goode, & William Foushee, etc., Directors of Public Buildings, provide information on work done to the Capitol Building and the settlement of accounts. On 28 November 1795, William Hay writes regarding the account of Samuel Dobie for superintending & directing the execution of the steps outside the Capitol, as well as the staircase, conference, and other work done inside the Capitol from 1793 to 1794. Hay also encloses accounts and a letter from Dobie indicating the amount of balances due him. On 30 March 1796, the Directors write regarding the repair of the roof of the Capitol and surplus materials.
Maj. Robert Quarles submits quarterly returns of ordnance & public stores at Point of Fork (1795 Jan. 2, 1795 March 31, 1795 June 30, 1795 Oct. 6, 1795 Dec. 31, 1796 March 31, 1796 June 30, & 1796 Sept. 30). In addition, Quarles' correspondence concerns a contract for provisions at Point of Fork (1795 May 5 & 25), an increase in salary (1795 Oct. 6), the bond of William Weaver to provide rations for the State Arsenal (1796 May 27), the supply of timber & firewood contract with David Ross (1796 Sept. 12), and the bond of Matthew & Elias Wills for the Office of Contractor to supply the State Arsenal with rations (1796 Oct. 27).
Thomas Newton, Jr., County Lieutenant for Norfolk Borough, frequently writes the Governor on a variety of concerns. On 11 January 1795, Newton encloses copies of letters from the British & French Consuls regarding disturbances between British & French crews in Norfolk Harbor. On 14 January, Newton discusses the case of Daniel Raybourn, an American seamen taken by the Lynx, a British ship of war, from a Danish Brig. He encloses the opinion of Alexander Campbell to the Lieutenant Governor on the same matter on 25 January 1795. In another letter, he remarks on Campbell's opinion on British deserters and the extradition of the fugitive Joseph Larelle back to Pennsylvania (1795 Feb. 1). Newton communicates Campbell's opinion to John Hamilton, British Consul, stating that it is the duty of the magistrates to apprehend deserters (1795 Feb. 2). An incident occurred in February 1795 when a group of armed men from the British ship Thetis marched into Norfolk committing illegal searches in the homes of citizens for deserters. Newton informs the Governor of this incident and encloses an account by the Captain of the Watch, a copy of a letter from John Hamilton, and depositions (1795 Feb. 17). He writes again on this matter on 25 February 1795 enclosing letters from Alexander F. Cochrane, Captain of the Thetis, & John Hamilton. Much of Newton's correspondence with Governor Brooke relates to the spread of diseases to Norfolk & the quarantine of vessels (1795 April 28; 1795 May 5, 16, 26; 1795 Aug. 22; 1795 Oct. 3; 1795 Nov. 4, 5, & 17; 1796 May 15 & 29; 1796 July 8; 1796 Aug. 13 & 28; 1796 Sept. 12 & 28; 1796 Oct. 27; & 1796 Nov. 7). On 28 February 1796, Newton writes regarding the purchase of two acres of land for building houses for the reception of goods and for accommodating the persons performing quarantine. On 17 April 1795, Newton informs the Governor of American citizens detained on board Admiral Murray's ship the Resolution, a British ship of war. His letters of 1796 Feb. 7 & 9 relate to letters from Henry McGeary, an American citizen impressed on the Resolution. Later, Newton encloses a letter from Judge Cyrus Griffin respecting the case of McGeary (1796 Feb. 21). Newton remarks on the arrival of three French ships from Guadalupe and the defenseless condition of the port due to the incompletion of the forts and the insufficient garrison there (1795 May 24). On 9 June 1795, Newton relates the capture of two French ships off the coast by the British ships Thetis & Hussar. In addition, he mentions the arrival of a French ship from Dominique with French citizens and a number of negroes which they claim as servants. A few days later, Newton informs the Governor of the arrival of the Sloop Industry from Boston which carried negro slaves on board in violation of the non-importation laws (1795 June 11). In a letter dated 21 June 1795, Newton encloses the deposition of Francis Marshal concerning two brigs taken off the coast of Virginia by a Bermudian privateer. Another significant event occurred in January 1796 when horses were purchased by British officers in the United States for mounting their troops against the French in the West Indies. Newton writes the Governor that this is a violation of the treaty with France & Holland (1796 Jan. 20). Shortly thereafter, he encloses a letter from Mr. Oster, French Consul, complaining of the shipment of horses by the British (1796 Jan. 23). The next day, he encloses one from John Hamilton denying that the shipment of horses is a military preparation (1795 Jan. 24).
Willis Wilson, County Lieutenant for Portsmouth, corresponds with the Governor regarding similar subjects as Thomas Newton. On 29 April 1795, Wilson suggests that a boat be armed at Hampton Roads for the purpose of preventing violators of U.S. neutrality and to liberate the men impressed on board Rear Admiral Murray's Squadron. He encloses the deposition of Capt. Hatten whose ship was boarded by the Lynx. A letter from Wilson to Admiral Murray relates to hostile expeditions by ships of any belligerent nation in Virginia waters. In this letter, he orders the ships to depart Virginia waters and to liberate any American citizens detained on board (1795 April 27). Wilson encloses a letter from John Hamilton informing him that the vessels Diana & Thomas are waiting to embark with their cargo of horses. On 24 June 1795, Wilson writes about the small pox epidemic in Portsmouth and the impressment of John Underwood & John Lloyd on board the British ship Lynx. Finally, Wilson writes the Governor regarding the formation of an artillery company in Portsmouth under the command of John Cowper (1796 Feb. 23 & March 27).
Governor Randolph corresponds often with John Pendleton, Jr., Auditor of Public Accounts, and Jaquelin Ambler, Treasurer, regarding various financial matters. Pendleton regularly encloses lists of warrants issued by him through the Auditor's Office (1795 March 31, 1795 July 1, 1795 Nov. 5, 1795 Dec. 31, 1796 July 1). Additionally, Pendleton writes regarding the suspicion of a fraudulent sale against Robert Craig, former sheriff of Washington County (1794 Dec. 18). Pendleton encloses the report of John Taylor and the opinion of John Marshall on the matter. Pendleton also writes to the Governor enclosing accounts of expenses of his office (1795 May 10). On 14 May 1795, Pendleton provided a report on the final settlement of William Davies' accounts as Commissioner of Virginia for Claims Against the United States. Pendleton submits his letter of resignation on 5 August 1796 effective at the end of the month. The next day, Pendleton recommends Samuel Shepard to replace him as Auditor. Pendleton's official letter of resignation was submitted on 30 Sept. 1796. Ambler encloses a statement of monies belonging to claimants for the defense of the Western frontier (1795 Aug. 27). In addition, on 24 September 1795, he encloses a copy of a letter from Samuel Meredith, U.S. Treasurer, regarding a warrant from the Secretary of War for the full balance due the State of Virginia for the settlement of their account for the pay & subsistence of militia, scouts, ammunition, and contingent expenses in the protection of the frontiers.
Notable correspondents from miscellaneous sources include the following: Andrew Dunscomb, Mayor of Richmond; John Hamilton, British Consul at Norfolk; and Thomas Mifflin, Governor of Pennsylvania.
Andrew Dunscomb mainly writes the Governor regarding the prevention of infectious disease to the City of Richmond. On 27 August 1795, he encloses resolutions of the Common Hall relative to the quarantine of vessels from Norfolk. Additionally, he discusses a law prohibiting the migration of free negroes from the West Indies into the Commonwealth (1795 Sept. 18). Dunscomb also transmits a letter from William Richardson & Jacob I. Cohen regarding allowing passage of vessels from Norfolk, but stopping vessels from New York (1795 Oct. 6).
John Hamilton, British Consul, frequently writes the Governor regarding British affairs. On 2 January 1795, Hamilton requests permission for the British ships Thetis & Cleopatra to make repairs in Norfolk Harbor. Hamilton also writes at length regarding British desertions, particularly the incident involving the attempt by British sailors on board the Thetis to recapture deserters in Norfolk (1795 Feb. 18, 25, & May 8). Hamilton was also particularly concerned with privateers preying on British ships. He specifically mentions a ship called the Unicorn which plundered a Danish vessel (1795 June 26 & July 30). In addition, Hamilton communicates his intelligence regarding vessels from Baltimore arming in the Chesapeake as privateers (1795 Aug. 15 & Sept. 24). His letter to the Lieutenant Governor relates to the prevention of illegal equipment for ships in the waters of Virginia (1795 July 3 & Oct. 6). Yet another incident occurred in January 1796 when the American Sloop Diana, loaded with British goods and bound for a British port in the West Indies, was forcibly boarded and her cargo carried away. Hamilton sends a letter to the Governor complaining about this incident, along with a similar letter to Willis Wilson (1796 Jan. 29). Finally, on 15 February 1796, Hamilton writes regarding his inquiry to the President on the shipment of horses and the neutrality laws.
As Governor of Pennsylvania, Thomas Mifflin often corresponds with Governor Brooke with respect to fugitives from justice. On 29 December 1794, Mifflin transmits the affidavit of Stephen Girard affirming that Joseph Larelle had taken a mulatto boy named Crispin from his service with an intention of selling him into slavery. He writes again on 10 February 1795 concerning the apprehension of Larelle. In a letter dated 12 March 1795, Mifflin informs the Governor of the appointment of Laurence Maher as Agent for Pennsylvania to bring Joseph Larelle back to Pennsylvania. Similarly, Mifflin transmits a copy of an affidavit by Robert Ross respecting Langford Herring who was accused of forgery and removed to Virginia (1795 Oct. 12). Mifflin also acknowledges the receipt of the revised laws from Virginia (1795 May 14 & 1796 Aug. 25) and a resolution from Virginia proposing certain amendments to the U.S. Constitution (1796 Jan. 6). Mifflin responds to another letter on 22 January 1796 regarding an annual interchange of the laws passed by Pennsylvania & Virginia.